A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, South Africa UPDATE Series Files FA1548
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, South Africa UPDATE Series Files
1980-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1548
7.76 Cubic Feet 19 Hollinger boxes
Scope and Contents
Collection is comprised of files pertaining to the preparation, production, and promotion of the South Africa UPDATE Series. The Ford Foundation initiated the UPDATE Series project in order to update the South Africa: Time Running Out report (SATRO) that was published in 1981 by the Study Commission on U.S. Policy Towards Southern Africa. The series consists of five monographs. Each book focuses on a particular theme regarding political developments in South Africa during the 1980s. Subjects covered in the series include international relations between South Africa and the United States, politics in the region of Southern Africa, political activism of black South Africans; reforms made to the Apartheid system, and the state of civil rights in South Africa.
Two of the five series in the collection contain the bulk of the collection's contents. They are Series 1. Chronological files and Series 4. Manuscripts and working files. The chronological files consist of correspondence, memos, drafts, invoices, purchase orders, expense reports, budget information, petty cash vouchers, agreements, and consultant requests. They document the work of the UPDATE Series Editor John de St. Jorre, Associate Editor Elinor Bowles, and Editorial Board in reaching out to prospective authors and readers of monographs, revising manuscripts, preparing the books' design, publishing and disseminating the books, and promoting the series. The manuscripts and working files series contains complete drafts of the writings included in several of the South Africa UPDATE monographs as well as readers' comments on the drafts, correspondence between the series' editors and the different authors, and supplementary materials to the writings. Some copies of the drafts have been saved to floppy disks.
The third and fourth series in the collection are chiefly comprised of the UPDATE Series editors' correspondence with monograph authors, research assistants, and monograph testimonial writers. Copies of monograph testimonials are also included in Series 3.
Lastly, the editorial files in Series 5 contain articles, newspaper clippings, reports, and publications that the series' editors more than likely collected for background information on the subjects discussed in the South Africa UPDATE books.
The collection contains materials from two different sets of records transferred to the RAC. The first set of material processed into the collection originated from a group of boxes containing Ford Foundation program strategy records. The documents' original storage containers and content indicated that the documents all concerned the South Africa UPDATE Series, so they were therefore processed as a discrete collection. They comprise Series 1-3 in the collection.
Another set of material related to the South Africa UPDATE Series was discovered at a later time within a group of boxes containing Ford Foundation publications. These records were added to the collection as Series 4 and 5.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of two different accessions: Accession 2019:046 Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records and Accession 2019:051, Ford Foundation records, Publications.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of five series. Records in the first three series originated from Accession 2019:046, Ford Foundation records, Program Strategy records, and records in the last two series originated from Accession 2019:051, Ford Foundation records, Publications.
Files in Series 1 were arranged in order to restore the intended chronological organization.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological files, 1986-1991
Series 2. Authors and research assistants' correspondence, 1990-1992
Series 3. Testimonials, 1989-1992
Series 4. Manuscripts and working files, 1983-1991
Series 5. Editorial files, 1980-1990
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation launched the South Africa UPDATE Series project in the late 1980s in order to update the South Africa: Time Running Out report (SATRO). The Study Commission on U.S. Policy Towards Southern Africa published the SATRO report in 1981. The Commission was funded by the Rockefeller Foundation and chaired by Ford Foundation President Franklin Thomas.
The UPDATE Series Editorial Board sought to update the SATRO report with a series of monographs that discussed recent political developments in South Africa. The Editorial Board emerged in part from the Ford Foundation's Southern Africa Study Group. Foundation staff members Franklin Thomas, Lynn Walker, and Gary Sick sat on the Board. John de St. Jorre served as Editor, Elinor Bowles served as Associate Editor, and Milfred Fierce served as Consulting Editor.
Monographs in the series concern topics like international relations between South Africa and the United States, politics in the region of Southern Africa, political activism of black South Africans; reforms made to the Apartheid system, and the state of civil rights in South Africa.
The five South Africa UPDATE monographs are titled:
The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years
All, Here, and Now: Black Politics in South Africa in the 1980s
Adapt or Die: The End of White Politics in South Africa
Changing Fortunes: War, Diplomacy, and Economics in Southern Africa
The Last Years of Apartheid: Civil Liberties in South Africa
Related Materials
The five published South Africa UPDATE Series monographs are available as part of the RAC's Library holdings
The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years
All, Here, and Now: Black Politics in South Africa in the 1980s
Adapt or Die: The End of White Politics in South Africa
Changing Fortunes: War, Diplomacy, and Economics in Southern Africa
The Last Years of Apartheid: Civil Liberties in South Africa
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Ford Foundation; Africa, Southern; Anti-apartheid movements -- South Africa; Apartheid; Civil rights -- South Africa; South Africa; South Africa -- Foreign relations -- United States
- Chronological files, 1986-1991; 1; 2.38 Cubic Feet About 6.25 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the chronological files that document the preparation, production, and promotion of the South Africa UPDATE Series. Correspondence, memos, drafts, invoices, purchases orders, expense reports, budget information, petty cash vouchers, agreements, and consultant requests document the work of the UPDATE Series Editor John de St Jorre, Associate Editor Elinor Bowles, and Editorial Board in hiring prospective monograph authors and readers, revising manuscripts, preparing the books' design, contracting organizations to co-publish and disseminate the books, and promoting the series. The editors and Editorial Board sought to promote the series through regional meetings, professional meetings, complimentary copies of monographs, monograph authors' appearances, and advertisements in publications. Meetings of the Editorial Board are also documented within the series.
  - Chronological file, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Chronological file, 1987 March-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological file, 1987 July-September (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological file, 1987 July-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological file, 1988 January-March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological file, 1988 April-June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chronological file, 1988 July-September (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Chronological file, 1988 October-December (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chronological file, 1989 January-March (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chronological file, 1989 April (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chronological file, 1989 May-June (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chronological file, 1989 July-September (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
  - Chronological file, 1989 October-November (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - Chronological file, 1989 December (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Chronological file, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Chronological file, 1990 February-April (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Chronological file, 1990 March-April (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Chronological file, 1990 April-May (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Chronological file, 1990 June (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Chronological file, 1990 July (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Chronological file, 1990 August (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Chronological file, 1990 September (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Chronological file, 1990 September-October (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Chronological file, 1990 November (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Chronological file, 1990 November-December (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Chronological file, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Chronological file, 1991 February (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Chronological file, 1991 March (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Chronological file, 1991 April (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Chronological file, 1991 May (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Chronological file, 1991 June (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Chronological file, 1991 July (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Chronological file, 1991 August (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Chronological file, 1991 July-September (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Chronological file, 1991 October (Box 6, Folder 41-42)
  - Chronological file, 1991 October-December (Box 6, Folder 43-44)
  - Chronological file, 1991 November-December (Box 7, Folder 45)
- Authors and research assistants' correspondence, 1990-1992; 2; .19 Cubic Feet About .5 LTR size Hollinger box
  Series contains correspondence between the South Africa UPDATE Series editors, Elinor Bowles and John de St. Jorre, and the series' different authors and research assistants. Correspondence generally regards the preparation and revisions of manuscripts, preparation of other components of the books such as footnotes and bibliographies, the distribution of authors' copies of published books, payments to authors, and promotion of the books.
  - Baker, Pauline, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Cheadle, Halton, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Clough, Michael, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Dugard, John, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Haysom, Nicholas, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Jaster, Robert, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Levin, Lydia, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Lodge, Tom, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Marcus, Gilbert, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Martin, Anthony, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Mbeki, Moeletsi, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Nasson, Bill, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Nkosi, Morley, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Schrire, Robert, 1990-1992 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Shubane, Khehla, 1991 March 6 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Sithole, Nokwanda, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Wilson, Lindy, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 62)
- Testimonials, 1989-1992; 3; .095 Cubic Feet About .25 LTR size Hollinger box
  Series contains correspondence between the South Africa UPDATE Series editors, Elinor Bowles and John de St. Jorre, and authors of the testimonials for the different books in the series as well as copies of the published testimonials. Correspondence documents the editors reaching out to the writers to see if they would be interested in writing a testimonial as well as the editors thanking the writers for their services.
  - Testimonial writers - All, Here, and Now: Black Politics in South Africa in the 1980s, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Testimonial - All, Here, and Now: Black Politics in South Africa in the 1980s, undated (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Testimonial writers - The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years, 1989 July 10 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Testimonial - The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years, undated (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Testimonial writers - Adapt or Die: The End of White Politics in South Africa, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Testimonial - Adapt or Die: The End of White Politics in South Africa, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Testimonial writers - Changing Fortunes: War, Diplomacy, and Economics in Southern Africa, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Testimonial - Changing Fortunes: War, Diplomacy, and Economics in Southern Africa, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Testimonial writers - The Last Years of Apartheid: Civil Liberties in South Africa, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Testimonial - The Last Years of Apartheid: Civil Liberties in South Africa, undated (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clipping, 1991 September 21 (Box 7, Folder 73)
- Manuscripts and working files, 1983-1991; 4; 3.46 Cubic Feet 6 LTR size and 2.5 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains the manuscripts and workings files that South Africa UPDATE Series editors Elinor Bowles and John de St. Jorre created in order to document the drafting and revising of the series' monographs. The manuscripts in the series are different drafts of writings used in several of the South Africa UPDATE books. Looking at these drafts, researchers can see how the writings changed over time through the process of editing and revising done by the editors and authors. The other files in the series contain correspondence between the editors and authors discussing revisions and improvements to the drafts, readers' comments on the drafts, and supplemental materials such as author biographies and footnotes.
  The records' creators used abbreviated terms to refer to the titles of the different monographs in the series. These abbreviations are:
  Black Politics (All, Here, and Now: Black Politics in South Africa in the 1980s)
  Region (Changing Fortunes: War, Diplomacy, and Economics in Southern Africa)
  White Politics (Adapt or Die: The End of White Politics in South Africa)
  The series does not contain any files specifically created to house documents for the other two South Africa UPDATE books, The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years and The Last Years of Apartheid: Civil Liberties in South Africa. However, one of the White Politics files does include some material related to The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years book.
  Future transfers of records to the RAC from the Ford Foundation may add more of this material to the collection.
  - Black Politics - Tom Lodge manuscript, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 74-75)
  - Black Politics - Tom Lodge manuscript, 1987 June 24 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Black Politics - Tom Lodge manuscript, 1987 June; File contains digital media. Digital media includes two 8 inch floppy disks. (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Dr. Tom Lodge "Black Politics" - Disk 1, pages 1-86, tables 1-2, undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Dr. Tom Lodge "Black Politics" - Disk 2, pages 87-159, undated (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Black Politics - Tom Lodge original manuscript, undated; File contains digital media. Digital media includes three 8 inch floppy disks. (Box 8, Folder 78-79)
  - Tom Lodge - Black Challenge, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Dr. Tom Lodge "Black Politics" - Disk 1, pages 1-86, tables 1-2, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Dr. Tom Lodge "Black Politics" - Disk 2, pages 87-159, undated (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Black Politics - Steve Mufson correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Black Politics - Steve Mufson, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Black Politics - Steve Mufson/Mono Badela, 1988-1990 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Black Politics - Steve Mufson introduction, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Black Politics - Steve Mufson biography, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson working file, 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson selected bibliography, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson revised manuscript, 1990 November 7 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1990 October 17 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1990 September 19 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, John de St. Jorre rewrite, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1990 April (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1990 March 19 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson, 1984-1987 (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1990; File contains digital media. Digital media includes one 3 1/2 and one 5 1/4 inch floppy disks. (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - William Nasson document, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - 045ly(Nasson), circa 1990; Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction. (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson manuscript, 1987 June (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Black Politics - William Nasson readers, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Black Politics - Jon Qwelane, 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - Black Politics - Permissions, 1990-1991 (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - Black Politics - Nokwanda Sithole manuscript, 1990 January (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - Black Politics - Nokwanda Sithole manuscript, 1990 April 6 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Black Politics - Lindy Wilson, 1990-1991; File contains digital media. Digital media includes one 3 1/2 and one 5 1/4 inch floppy disks. (Box 10, Folder 102-103)
  - Robben Island document, undated (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - 0450y(RobbenI), undated (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Black Politics - Khehla Shubane, 1988-1991 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Black Politics - Soweto, South Africa section reprinted materials, 1984-1991 (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - Mono Badela/Steve Mufson (revised), undated (Box 11)
  - Region - Robert Jaster manuscript, 1990 January (Box 11, Folder 106)
  - Region - Robert Jaster manuscript, 1990 January (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Region - Robert Jaster summary of South Africa: Time Running Out (SATRO) Chapter 11, 1988 April 7 (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - Region - John de St. Jorre introduction, 1990 January (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - Region - Gillian Gunn, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Region - Appendices, 1984-1990 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi, 1987-1989 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi manuscript, 1988 October 6 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi manuscript, 1988 September (Box 12, Folder 115)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi summary of South Africa: Time Running (SATRO) Chapter 12, 1988 April 7 (Box 12, Folder 116)
  - Region - Moeletsi Mbeki/Morley Nkosi summary of South Africa: Time Running (SATRO) Chapter 12, undated (Box 12, Folder 117)
  - Region - Readers, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 118)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy working file, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy, 1986-1989 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy manuscript, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy manuscript, 1989 March 21 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy manuscript, 1988 November 16 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy manuscript, 1989 April 13 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Region - Southern African Development Coordination Conference (SADCC), 1990 (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Region - Tim Sheehy, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1991 March 11 (Box 13, Folder 127)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire working file, 1990-1991 (Box 13, Folder 128)
  - White Politics - Southern African Development Coordination Conference (SADCC) Food, Agriculture, and Natural Resources, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire correspondence, 1986-1991 (Box 13, Folder 130)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1991 January 10 (Box 13, Folder 131)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire summary of South Africa: Time Running Out (SATRO) Chapter 10, 1987 May 6 (Box 13, Folder 132)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire summary of South Africa: Time Running Out (SATRO) Chapter 10, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 133)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire readers, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 134)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1991 March 15 (Box 14, Folder 135)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire biography, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript footnotes, undated (Box 14, Folder 137)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire readers, 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 138)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire other writings, 1983-1990 (Box 14, Folder 139)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1990 January (Box 14, Folder 140)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 141)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript at joint session at Ford Foundation, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 142-143)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1989 November (Box 15, Folder 144-145)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1988 March 1 (Box 15, Folder 146)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire, 1987-1988; File contains digital media. Digital media includes one 5 1/4 inch floppy disk. (Box 15, Folder 147)
    File contains some material related to The United States and South Africa: The Reagan Years monograph.
  - Pauline Baker - United States/South Africa (first draft), 1987 February 17 (Box 15, Folder 147)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript, 1987 November (Box 15, Folder 148)
  - White Politics - Robert Schrire manuscript revisions, 1986-1987; File contains digital media. Digital media includes one 8 inch floppy disk. (Box 15, Folder 149)